Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ל. Lamed. We
pick up at the גמרא Gemara after the משנה Mishnah on כט
עמוד ב, Kaf-Tet Amud Bet, with כט עמוד ב Kaf-Tet Amud Bet
with the משנה Mishnah on כט עמוד ב. Kaf-Tet Amud Bet. We're
entering in to a new section of the גמרא, Gemara, like a
section that really focuses on forbidden foods, which is of a very
different nature. Are some of them related to עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
Maybe, but it's of, as opposed to the past where it was
about issues about interactions, selling things, going to markets or whatever, here
the concern is, it really doesn't matter where you get this from,
the concern is what the object itself. It's very, very object-focused. I
mean, the most we had some object-focused before, it was selling them
things they would use for
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, selling them animals or whatever like this. Anyway,
here it's things that we get from them and the real concern
here is כשרות. Kashrus. Now, כשרות Kashrus can be of one of
two ways, meaning כשרות Kashrus could be of things that we know
are non-kosher foods that are mixed in. That's not so much this
משנה. Mishnah. That's going to be a משנה Mishnah coming up which
are things that are forbidden to be eaten but permissible to derive
benefit from, מותר בהנאה. mutar b'hana'ah. So that shows it's basically just
a כשרות Kashrus concern. This משנה Mishnah is like a good transition
משנה Mishnah because this משנה Mishnah are things that you can't derive
benefit, and if you can't derive benefit, that almost definitely signals the
fact that it's a concern that it has something to do with
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And the first major thing has to do
with the wine. And then there's this whole fascinating discussion at the
end about cheese, which we'll get to when we see it.
They go together. Exactly. That's a very good point. Exactly, that's why
they אסרed assur cheese because of wine. Good point, touché. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara here at the after the משנה Mishnah on כט
עמוד ב. Kaf-Tet Amud Bet. יין מנלן? Yayin mi-nalan? Where do we
know that wine of non-Jews is forbidden? אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
קרא, Amar Rabba bar Avuha amar kra, the verse says, אשר חלב
זביחימו יאכלו ישתו יין נסיכם, Asher chelev zivcheimo yocheilu yishtu yein nesicham,
they will eat the fat of their sacrifices, they will drink the
wine of their, what they call, not anointing, not anointing, that's another,
libations. מה זבח אסור בהנאה, Ma zevach assur b'hana'ah,
so the sacrifice, the meat of a sacrifice, the fat is compared
to a wine that is used in a libation to idolatry. So
the same way the actual sacrifice is forbidden, אף יין נמי אסור
בהנאה, af yayin nami assur b'hana'ah, wine is the same. So the
גמרא Gemara says, זבח גופיה מנלן? Zevach gufeih mi-nalan? Now, how do
we know that something that's offered as a sacrifice to another god
is forbidden? דכתיב, De-chtiv, the verse says, ויצמדו לבעל פעור ויאכלו זבחי
מתים, Vayitzmadu l'Baal Peor vayochlu zivchei meisim, they cleaved unto Baal Peor
and they ate the sacrifices of the dead. So interesting what does
the word מתים meisim mean? So halachically we're interpreting it, מה מת
אסור בהנאה, ma meis assur b'hana'ah, the same way you can't derive
benefit from a dead body, אף זבח נמי אסור בהנאה, af zevach
nami assur b'hana'ah,
the same is true by a sacrifice. Interesting whole question about doing
autopsies and using dead bodies for medical education. Why is that allowed?
Is that considered a type of a benefit? Might be that benefit
is defined more narrowly, so something like intellectual benefit which for some
people is the highest form of benefit might technically not be considered
הנאה hana'ah because it's not bodily benefit or financial benefit. Anyway, just
a totally parenthetical comment. It's the opposite of the dead. You're learning
that to live. Yeah, that's true. That is true. Okay, anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says like this. ומת גופיה מנלן? U-meis gufeih mi-nalan? Now
how do you know that a dead body you're not allowed to
get הנאה hana'ah from? We keep on going down the road here.
אתיא שם שם מעגלה ערופה, Atya sham sham me-eglah arufah, it's a
link to the calf that you break its neck. כתיב הכא ותמת
שם מרים, K-siv hacha vatamos sham Miriam,
Miriam died there, so that's about death. וכתיב התם וערפו שם את
העגלה בנחל, U-chsiv hatam v'arfu sham et ha'eglah banachal, you break the
neck of the עגלה, eglah, I always do that, thank you, וערפו
שם את העגלה בנחל, v'arfu sham et ha'eglah banachal, you break the
neck of the calf in the wadi. So מה להלן אסור בהנאה,
ma le-halan assur b'hana'ah, the same way you can't derive benefit from
the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, אף כאן נמי אסור בהנאה. af kan
nami assur b'hana'ah. So you can't derive benefit from the dead body.
Of course the next question is going to be והתם מנלן? Ve-hatam
mi-nalan? And how do you know you can't derive benefit from the
עגלה ערופה? eglah arufah? אמר דבי רבי ינאי כפרה כתיב בה כקדשים.
Amar d'bei Rabbi Yannai kappara ksiv bah ke-kodashim. It says כפר לעמך
ישראל. Kapper l'amcha Yisrael. So if it's to be used for a
type of an atonement, the same way we know you can't derive
benefit from sacrifices, thank God the גמרא Gemara stopped there. Okay, could
have said how do you know you can't derive benefit from sacrifices?
But anyway. Who did we start with? Wasn't it? No, but it
means, thank you, it means our sacrifices. You're right. It's actually interesting,
I didn't realize that we got all the way back to our
sacrifices. Anyway, so therefore you can't do it all by the עגלה
ערופה. eglah arufah. So since the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah you can't
derive benefit, we link it to something dead. Since you can't derive
benefit from a dead body, you can't derive benefit from a sacrifice
to the dead or a sacrifice to the gods, and therefore you
can't derive benefit from wine. So that's a very fascinating link. Now
the point though is, the important question is, is that what, but
we're not talking about wine that was given as a libation to
the gods. We're talking here about just wine that was handled, touched,
processed, made by non-Jews. So the clear implication is, is that סתם
יינם, stam yeinam, there's two terms in הלכה: Halacha: יין נסך, yayin
nesech, wine that was actually יין נסיכם. yein nesicham. was used as
a libation, and
סתם יינם, stam yeinam, their normal one, and the sense is we
didn't allow normal wine of theirs for us to get benefit from
or to drink because of a concern, or either concern that it
was סתם, stam, I say that it was יין נסך, yayin nesech,
or an expansion of the category, we're not really concerned but just
a way to sort of keep off the same way you don't
have meat and milk and you wait six hours between meat and
milk, not necessarily a concern that it'll lead to the other thing,
but we're just expanding the category, protecting -- meat, what'd I say?
The cheese and milk? Oh for God's sake, meat and milk. Anyway,
you know what I meant. Anyway, we're just expanding the category and
here too expanding the category to include for all of their wine.
Now תוספות Tosfos asks a very critical question. Let's take a look
at this first תוספות. Tosfos. יין מנלן, Yayin minalan, says תוספות Tosfos
תימא מאי קבעי מנלן. teima mai ka ba'i minalan. What do you
mean where do you know it from? המניתין מאי בסתם יינם, Hamisnitin
mai bistam yeinam, our משנה Mishnah is talking about their wine that
is not used for any part -- you know, we don't have
a reason to say it was used specifically for some idolatrous purpose.
וגזירה דרבנן היא, Vegezeira deRabbanan hi, and it's not because of a
concern of יין נסך, yayin nesech, it's a רבנן Rabbanan restriction, wine
שגזרו על יינם משום בנותיהם, shegazru al yeinam mishum bnoseihem, that it's
a concern that it'll lead to intermarriage, that it'll lead to too
much socializing. Wine is a, you know, if the Rabbis were around
nowadays, they'd forbid
beer or something of that nature. Actually, it is interesting, there is
a גמרא Gemara that does seem to forbid drinking any alcohol with
non-Jews, but we'll put that aside for a moment, we'll get to
that. Okay, anyway, but wine was certainly, was definitely something that was
seen as a primary sort of social lubricant as they call it,
and you start drinking wine with non-Jews and even buying -- if
you're not drinking with them, buying from it, one thing leads to
another, it'll lead to intermarriage. Okay? So it's not about a concern
about the thing that was offered to the gods. So תוספות Tosfos
says ויש לומר דודאי עיקר גזירה דסתם יינם משום בנותיהם. veyesh lomar
devaday ikar gezeira destam yeinam mishum bnoseihem. The real reason they forbid
it, you're right, is because of their daughters, which is a way
of saying over-socializing and intermarriage and so הוא. hu. מיהו לא היו
עושים אותו בהנאה מטעם זה. Mihu lo hayu osim oso behana'ah mita'am
zeh. That would have only limited to saying don't drink it, it
wouldn't have said don't derive הנאה, hana'ah, right? If it was just
as a barrier to socializing. מידי דהוי אפיתן ושמנן, Midi dehavei apisan
ushmanam, the same way their bread and their oil and other things,
אלא עבדו רבנן כיין נסך גמור שניסך לפני עבודת כוכבים שאסור מן
התורה משום דדמי ליה. ela avdu Rabbanan k'yayin nesech gamur shenisasech lifnei
avodat kochavim sheasur min hatorah mishum d'dami lei. Okay. ועל יין נסך
שלא תלמוד מנלן. Ve'al yayin nesech shelo talmud minalan. But what we
did is we upped it one stage and we said but since
it's already their wine, their wine is similar to wine, their wine
of sacrifices, so therefore we're going to add our prohibition of הנאה.
hana'ah. So this is the general story about their wine and it
really depends how you interpret the facts. There's גמרות Gemaras that sound
like the issue of their wine has to do with עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, again just an extension of the עבודה זרה avoda zara
category, an extension of יין נסך. yayin nesech. There's other גמרות Gemaras
that sound like the issue of their wine has to do with
בנותיהם, bnoseihem, socializing and intermarriage concern. So the question is, the normal
approach ראשונים rishonim say is like you start, you know, both are
true or both were part of the תקנה takkana and you know
maybe at different times in history first they did one then they
did the other. Now the easier thing to say is what תוספות
Tosfos says, because if they first did the one that it was
based on עבודה זרה avoda zara and you couldn't derive הנאה, hana'ah,
why do you also need to say that it's about socializing? You've
already made it totally off limits. So the easier way to tell
the story, if you have these two different sort of explanations, is
the way תוספות Tosfos tells the story: that it starts with a
concern about socializing, you know, and intermarriage or whatever and then it's
just forbidden to drink, and then they added another layer to make
it even more off limits to say don't derive הנאה. hana'ah. Okay,
but it's a question whether that's really the full historical explanation. Again,
there's like interesting academic literature about how to deal with the fact
there's two different versions about why it's forbidden, but the general understanding
is whatever the historical arc is, it's in both categories. Now the
question is once they have the second category or the first category,
whatever it is, don't derive הנאה, hana'ah, does the category of בנותיהם,
bnoseihem, intermarriage, matter? And the answer is yes. Can you think of
a scenario where it would matter that we had the category of
intermarriage even though we've already said the category of don't derive הנאה
hana'ah -- you can't even get הנאה hana'ah from it because it
might be related to עבודה זרה? avoda zara? Can you think why
it still matters that we say there's an idea of intermarriage? What
scenario would not have a problem, a possible problem of עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, but would have the problem of intermarriage? Can you think
of one? Wait, which one? Sorry. Islam? What? Islam, right! Or let's
take a case in the גמרא. Gemara. How about a גר תושב?
Ger Toshav? How about wine of somebody that's in a category that
we acknowledge that the definition of this category is a non-Jew that
isn't עובד עבודה זרה? oved avoda zara? A גר תושב. Ger Toshav.
So why should it be forbidden בהנאה? behana'ah? And the basic point
is that it isn't, but you still can't drink it because there's
still intermarriage concerns. And רמב"ם Rambam uses this to say that for
Islam you can buy their wine and sell their wine, you can
do business with their wine, of course the question is what are
they doing with wine, they're not supposed to have wine either, but
okay they. They weren't, the same way they're not פרום Frum Jews,
they're also not פרום Frum Muslims. Anyway, so you can buy and
sell wine from Muslims,
but you cannot drink it. So it actually does matter that there
are both categories, and the הנאה Hana'a category is only for עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara type of concerns. And then it leads to when
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara concerns are relevant. And then it leads to
questions that I mentioned since the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet, the
whole discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim that Christians nowadays are not עובדי
עבודה זרה, Ovdei Avoda Zara, whether wine from Christians also in some
cases we could be lenient and would allow somebody to get benefit
from. Not to drink, but to get benefit from. So it really
does matter that there are two categories here. The question historically is
which one was the real one, or the original one, or
whatever, is an open question. We'll start with Charlie, yes. I'm 90%
of the way through the Arabian Nights, which was set in the
early Middle Ages. Okay.
And Muslims are drinking wine all the time. There you go. So
I wonder whether that was a later prohibition. Well,
the prohibition is from the time of- oh, you mean for Muslims.
Oh, that I don't know, I don't know, but anyway, yes. My
question is this, because I'm really curious about this, because what about
stuff processed with grape juice? Like, Tropicana, whatever it is, and they
have a little bit of grape juice? Okay, so we're going to
take a look at how you define wine. So the focus of
today's דף Daf is how you define wine. So let's hold that.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Can we make sure
we address it? Yes.
Okay. וחומץ של עובדי כוכבים שהיה מתחילתו יין. Vechometz shel ovdei chochavim
shehaya mitchilato yayin. So now we get to the next stage, which
is not only wine, but even- we're not dealing yet with grape
juice, we'll get to that, but even vinegar, wine vinegar. If it
started as wine. Now of course wine vinegar always starts as wine,
maybe it's to contrast it with other vinegars. Cider. Okay. Or רש"י
Rashi says it's to contrast to a case where they didn't have
it originally when it was wine. They bought it from us as
wine vinegar, then it's not a problem. If a non-Jew owns or
touches or handles wine vinegar, it's not a problem. It's only a
problem when they originally had it in their possession as wine. So
the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא. Peshita. Obviously. משום דאחמיץ פקע ליה איסוריה? Mishum de'achmetz paka lei
issurei? Once it began as forbidden, once it got its forbidden status-
and this by the way is the difference between whether we focus
on the object or the person and the interaction. If you focus
on the person and the interaction you say, 'well when you buy
it, it's fine.' But if we focus on the object, like if
something was חזיר, Chazir, just because now it's a little changed, of
course it's still חזיר. Chazir. If it's still edible. So just because
the wine became vinegar, if it was אסור Assur if they had
it originally as wine and it was אסור, Assur, it doesn't stop
being אסור Assur because it became vinegar. Well, but you think it's
a matter of socializing. But okay, but that is the point. We
don't. And even the socializing approach in the end has a status
about the object. So we have really shifted now to talking about
not interactions, but about defining whatever the background is, the object is
forbidden in benefit or the object is forbidden to be eaten. So
the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא משום דאחמיץ פקע ליה איסוריה, Peshita mishum
de'achmetz paka lei issurei, just because it became vinegar the prohibition goes
away? אמר רב אשי הכא לאשמועינן, Amar Rav Ashi hacha le'ashme'inan, it's
coming to teach us, חומץ שלנו ביד עובדי כוכבים אין צריך חותם
בתוך חותם. Chometz shelanu beyad ovdei chochavim ein tzarich chotam betoch chotam.
I'm sorry, I skipped, no. חומץ שלנו ביד עובדי כוכבים אין צריך
חותם בתוך חותם. Chometz shelanu beyad ovdei chochavim ein tzarich chotam betoch
chotam. If we give our vinegar to a non-Jew and ask him
to be our middleman and to sell it or to watch it
for us, we don't need a double seal. They had double wrappings
back then. But a double seal is just like each seal you
sort of do a special way, so you see that if the
seal is broken you can tell it's been tampered with. And if
somebody- like they do now, the safety seal, so you can see
if it's been tampered. And if somebody wanted to break it and
to take the thing inside, they would have to go to the
trouble of forging and making a new replacement seal. So some cases
which we really, really have to protect, we're really afraid the non-Jew
will want to maybe get into the contents and take it for
himself and replace it with some inferior product which will be not
kosher, we required a double seal to make it really impossible, the-
way too high of a cost for him to try to tamper
with. But what- but here we're saying a single seal is enough.
You don't need a double seal. Why is that? They're watching our
vinegar, a single seal is enough. אי משום ניסוכי, Ei mishum nisuchi,
let's be afraid that when they have our vinegar maybe they'll use
it for libations? לא מנסכי. Lo menaschi. So telling us that if
they're holding on to wine vinegar that they never had as wine,
it's okay, means we are not concerned that they'll use vinegar for
their libations. So that's important principle number one. And if libations is
off the table, again this sees it only through the lens of
libations, not through the lens of בנותיהם Benoteihem and so on.
Okay. ואי משום איחלופי. Ve'ei mishum ichlufi. Now let's say we should
be afraid that maybe we have high quality vinegar and they're going
to take- swap it for low quality vinegar, which might not be
kosher? So then, כיון דאיכא חותם לא טרח ומזייף. Keivan de'ika chotam
lo tarach umezayef. No, it has one seal, one seal is enough.
So meaning the idea of one seal being enough is completely not
relevant to our משנה. Mishnah. That's a second גמרא. Gemara. That if
there's just סתם stam a concern, maybe if they think that this
is oh my god this is a beautiful thing I want to
use it for my עבודה זרה avodah zarah we need a double
seal in order to protect it because they're highly motivated. But something
that's just, you know, maybe some financial benefit, I'll take this, it's
expensive, I'll replace it with something cheaper, the general assumption is, barring
exceptional cases, a single seal is enough. Okay, so that's really not
the discussion, except certain things that they're highly motivated, like things they
might want to use for עבודה זרה avodah zarah might be a
different story. Okay, so the basic point that a single seal is
enough here is like parenthetical. The real point is, is that if
they're handling our vinegar, we don't have to be afraid that their
handling of it makes it forbidden because they don't use that for
type of נסך. nesekh. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רב אילא שנינו, Amar Rav Ilo sheninu, we taught,
יין מבושל yayin mevushal של עובדי כוכבים shel ovdei kokhavim שהיה מתחלתו
יין אסור. she-hayah mitichilato yayin assur. So here we get the יין
מבושל, yayin mevushal, right, all of the wine, so much of the
wine we have is יין מבושל yayin mevushal which makes it taste
not as good, but then it means that it doesn't matter if
it's handled after it's cooked by a non-Jew because once it's been
cooked, it's not going to be used for libations. Okay, so then,
but what he says is, but if it started, if they first
had the wine and handled the wine and produced the wine and
then they cooked it, okay, or owned the wine, then it's a
problem, then it already became forbidden and it doesn't stop being forbidden.
Okay, so יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, so the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא,
peshita, obviously, משום דאיתבשל פקע ליה איסורא? mishum d'itvashal pakle issura? What,
you think because you cooked it, like if you take חזיר khazir
from non-Jews and you cook it, you think it becomes כשר kosher
because it was cooked? Okay, if it was, so that's the point,
because we're focusing on the status of the object that doesn't go
away. So אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, no no no, the
point is, יין מבושל שלנו ביד עובדי כוכבים, yayin mevushal she-lanu b'yad
ovdei kokhavim, that if it started with us as יין מבושל yayin
mevushal and now they're owning it and handling it or watching it,
then it does not become forbidden. And this is of course what
is critical. The idea that we don't care, once it's cooked, it's
okay to be handled by non-Jews, is based on this גמרא. Gemara.
אין צריך חותם ביד חותם, Ein tzorikh khotam biyad khotam, you don't
need a double seal. אם משום ניסוכי, Im mishum nissukhei, if we're
afraid that they'll use it for libations, and this is more reasonable
than the concern of vinegar, this we might have thought this is
still wine. So it's telling us, no, לא מנסכי, lo menaskhi, they
don't use it for libations. ואם משום חילופי, Ve-im mishum chilufei, we're
afraid they might exchange it for something more expensive, which then would
actually be forbidden wine. For something more cheap, thank you, which would
actually be forbidden
wine. כיוון דאיכא חותם אחד לא טרחו ומזייפי, Keivan d'ika khotam echad
lo tarchu mezayef, one seal is enough if it's not some high
motivation to exchange it, just like oh they want to exchange something
expensive for ours for something cheaper theirs, one seal is enough. So
the basic חידוש khiddush here is יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, sealed יין
מבושל, yayin mevushal, that's what it is. Sealed, well that the חותם
khotam you only need to know that they didn't exchange it. Okay,
but if you know they didn't exchange it otherwise, if you're keeping
your eyes on it and they're handling your wine but it's already
יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, it's okay. So the חותם khotam is just
to eliminate concerns that they exchanged it. Put that aside. The bigger
point for us is that once, if they owned it, then cooking
it afterwards doesn't change the status, you know, or produced it or
touched it or whatever. But if first we got it cooked, now
it's safe. Now it can be owned or touched or whatever by
non-Jews, it does not become forbidden. Now here by the way is
another reason why it's really important that we have both statuses of
the יין נסך yayin nesekh category and the בנותיהם bnoteihem category. Because
if we only had the בנותיהם bnoteihem category, we could have reasonably
said that you'll still socialize. Now maybe you could have come up
with an argument and you could have said, you know, because it's
so inferior once you cook it, you know, it's no longer an
important drink and therefore you won't come to socialize as much. Maybe,
and maybe there's some truth to that, but at the end of
the day, the reason is is since it can't fit into the
יין נסך yayin nesekh category, it's just completely not in any category
of wine. So it's actually interesting. If the person who's handling it
is a non-Jew who's not עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, גר
תושב ger toshav or whatever, then it's just it's okay, it's forbidden
because it's just in the בנותיהם bnoteihem category, but it's only forbidden
to drink not to get benefit. But we can have something that
lives just in the בנותיהם bnoteihem category. But if it's the wine,
if the wine doesn't fit in the יין נסך yayin nesekh category
because it's not wine used in libations, then it's totally okay. We
don't even put it in the בנותיהם bnoteihem category. So that's why
יין מבושל yayin mevushal is actually okay and it's not in both
categories because it's not in the עבודה זרה avodah zarah category. And
for some reason that they use to determine, you know, whether it
was a problem even for the issues of intermarriage and so on.
Yes. יין מבושל Yayin mevushal is now used for communion in most
Christian churches. Really? Why is it? Because it's cheaper? It's not cheaper.
Well, actually they mostly use grape juice, which is pasteurized. Oh, so
there, okay. So, interesting.
Okay, there you go. Okay, I don't know what, אוי, oy, I
don't know what to say to that. Don't, don't say those things
to me. Yes. Okay, so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. I
have someone who used to be an עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah
zarah. There you go, אוי. oy. Anyway. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught,
okay? Okay. One minute.
Yeah, okay, fine. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught: יין מבושל ואלונתית
של עובדי כוכבים אסורין. Yayin mevushal ve'alontit shel ovdei kochavim assurim. So
their cooked wine is forbidden. Now that's different than we just taught,
but not really, because what it means is של עובדי כוכבים shel
ovdei kochavim means it started as not מבושל mevushal and then they
cooked it. Okay, so as we said, if it started as a
problem and then you cooked it, it doesn't—the problem doesn't go away.
Similar אלונתית, alontit, which is a type of a mixture of stuff
that they put into the wine, you know, all these
different—I don't know, fragrances and other types of things. Okay, the גמרא's
Gemara I think going to explain the stuff they put in it.
It doesn't matter. Once it started as wine, it remains forbidden as
wine.
Okay. אסורין. Assurim. אלונתית כברייתה, Alontit kevriyata, if however it is this
original אלונתית, alontit, מותרת. muteret. It's permissible. Now what does it mean
original? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says what it means is if they
originally came into possession of it after it was mixed. Like if
they originally came into possession of it after it was cooked, then
already it's not a type of thing they would use for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah and it's okay. תוספות Tosafot says what it means
is that the way you would do it is you would sort
of do it like, you know, reconstituted milk or grape juice or
whatever, orange juice, is that—not reconstituted exactly, but you would make it,
you would have the mixture and you would have the wine, and
when it came time to do the ointment or whatever it is,
you'd mix the two together. So for תוספות, Tosafot, אלונתית כברייתה alontit
kevriyata means all the additives without yet the wine. So if you
just have the additives and you don't have the wine, that's permissible,
with the answer to that is, okay, duh, but anyway. Okay, but
the point is is that this is like מבושל. mevushal. Once it's
mixed, it doesn't—if it's already forbidden, mixing it doesn't make it okay.
But if it's mixed and then they handle it or whatever or
own it, it's not a problem because it's not used for עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. And now the גמרא Gemara continues: ואיזהו אלונתית? Ve'eizehu
alontit? What is this אלונתית? alontit? כדתניא, kidtanya, like we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraita, גבי שבת: gabbei Shabbat: עושין אנומלין ואין עושין אלונתית.
Osin anumalin ve'ein osin alontit. On שבת Shabbat you can make this
mixture of
אנומלין anumalin or whatever it is, אנומלין, anumalin, which is some type
of a mixture with wine which would be drunk, okay? רש"י Rashi
says it's with honey. With honey. Oh, I'm sorry, the גמרא's Gemara
going to say it. All right, I'm sorry, I forgot it. Oh,
it's wine and honey, see we're both right. Anyway, you can make
this mixture of wine and honey which is to drink on שבת
Shabbat because you're just doing it to drink and there's no איסור
issur of mixing the two liquids together. But you can't make this
אלונתית alontit on שבת Shabbat because אלונתית alontit was used for medicinal
purposes. And we already learned that medicinal—anyone would drink it? Right. And
things that are used for medicinal purposes, okay, and as you say,
a type of an ointment or whatever, you're not allowed to make
medicines on שבת, Shabbat, okay?
ואיזהו אנומלין ואיזהו אלונתית? Ve'eizehu anumalin ve'eizehu alontit? Which is which? אנומלין
יין ודבש ופלפלין: Anumalin yayin u'devash u'pilpelin: wine and honey and pepper.
Okay, and therefore anyway that's like some spiced wine. That you can
make on שבת, Shabbat, that's just a drink. אלונתית יין ישן ומים
צלולין ואפרסמון: Alontit yayin yashan u'mayim tzlulim ve'aparsimon: old wine and מים
צלולין mayim tzlulim and אפרסמון, aparsimon, which is—what's אפרסמון aparsimon again? Persimmon?
בשמן? Bosem? Balsam? Balsam? Persimmon? Now we call it a persimmon. Not
the persimmon. Maybe it's balsam.
Balsam is a type of a wood. Okay, anyway, I don't know.
It stays three to five meter high bush. All right, fine. Okay.
דאבדי לבי מסותא, De'avdi lebei masuta, and they use this, and they
use this—fine,
fine. Anyway, and they use this for what do you call it?
For going to
the—to cool off, you know, after going to like the—after bathing or
something like that. All right. So anyway, so the point is is
that this is a mixture. Because the mixture is not used for
drinking, it's even used for like medicinal purposes, it's okay if they
handle it after it's been mixed, it's no longer wine really. It's
certainly not wine—it's certainly not better than יין מבושל. yayin mevushal. It's
not wine that you would use for—for, you know, libations. But if
they first had it and then it got mixed, it remains forbidden.
All right. Now the גמרא Gemara switches gears for most of the
rest of the גמרא. Gemara. Now we got the basic idea about
יין, yayin, we'll get—we'll get a little bit later to the grape
juice issue. But now for most of the גמרא Gemara we switch
to a different concern. Not a concern of—of,
you know, the יין נסך yayin nesech or the סתם יינם, stam
yeinam, but a concern of גילוי, gilluy, of wine or foods that
are left exposed that the גמרא Gemara was said you can't eat
it out of danger, concern that a snake would have come and
drank from it or eaten from it and left behind some poison.
You know, which could have really been just a misinterpretation of facts,
that it was a concern of like bacteria and other things and
they saw that people got sick sometimes and that's how they interpreted
it. But that led to this whole category of things which was—which
became real הלכה, halacha, you know, it's not just so other types
of statements in the גמרא Gemara which are like, "Oh, be careful
because it's a danger," but like it's never framed in הלכה halacha
terms. Here, it's framed in a whole range of הלכה halachic terminology
and, you know, categories, this issue of גילוי. giluy. Nevertheless, תוספות Tosafot
basically rules none of this applies nowadays, we don't have the same
concern with snakes, since it's ultimately anchored in this type of medical,
you know, health-based concern, which תוספות Tosafot felt was no longer relevant.
Okay, anyway, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
רבא ורב יוסף דרמי תרוייהו, Rava and Rav Yosef darmi tavaihu, רבא
Rava and רב יוסף Rav Yosef both say,
יין מזוג, yayin mazug, mixed wine, like with water, אין בו משום
גילוי ein bo mishum giluy is not a concern of being exposed.
Snakes only like the strong stuff. יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, cooked, אין
בו משום ניסוך ein bo mishum nisuch is not a problem of
יין נסך yayin nesech of wine of non-Jews as we've said, if
that's if they get it first when it's cooked.
So the גמרא Gemara says, איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, so the, I'm
sorry, did I skip a line? רבא ורב יוסף דרמי תרוייהו, Rava
and Rav Yosef darmi tavaihu, יין מזוג אין בו משום גילוי, yayin
mazug ein bo mishum giluy, יין מבושל אין בו משום ניסוך. yayin
mevushal ein bo mishum nisuch. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they asked the
question: יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, so what about the cross categories? יש
בו משום גילוי? yesh bo mishum giluy? How about יין מבושל, yayin
mevushal, is that a problem leaving it exposed? Is that a problem,
do snakes like יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, או אין בו משום גילוי?
o ein bo mishum giluy? And then the other question is about,
is about, you know, what would you say about mixed wine and
about יין נסך, yayin nesech, but that presumed so we're going to
ask those things. תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear: הי רב
יעקב בר אידי, he Rav Yaakov bar Idi, יין מבושל שאין בו
משום גילוי. yayin mevushal she-ein bo mishum giluy. He said cooked wine
is not a problem for snakes, the same way it's not a
problem for יין נסך, yayin nesech, it's not a problem for exposing.
רב ינאי בר ישמעאל חלש, Rav Yannai bar Yishmael chalash, רב ינאי
בר ישמעאל Rav Yannai bar Yishmael got sick. עלו גבי רב ישמעאל
בן זירוד, alu gabei Rav Yishmael ben Zirud, whoever that is, ורבנן
לשיוליה ביה, ve-rabanan lishuyilei beih, they went to, you know, visit him,
inquire after his health. יתיב וקא מיבעיא ליה, yasiv ve-ka ibaya lei,
so he was sick and they were sitting and they were asking,
מיבעיא להו: mi-baya lehu: יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, יש בו משום גילוי
או אין בו משום גילוי? yesh bo mishum giluy o ein bo
mishum giluy? יין מבושל, yayin mevushal, is it a problem of exposing
or not? אמר להו רבי ישמעאל בן זירוד, amar lehu Rabbi Yishmael
bar Zirud, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said, הכי אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש משום גברא רבא, hachi amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish mishum gavra
raba, this was ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said in the name of
a great person, ומנו רבי חייא, u-manu Rabbi Chiya, in the name
of רבי חייא: Rabbi Chiya: יין מבושל אין בו משום גילוי, yayin
mevushal ein bo mishum giluy, it's not a problem of גילוי. giluy.
אמרו ליה, amru lei, so they said to him, to presumably this
רב ינאי בר ישמעאל, Rav Yannai bar Yishmael, נסמוך, nismoch, can we
rely on this teaching? You know, because it came from this רבי
ישמעאל בן זירוד Rabbi Yishmael bar Zirud who maybe he was not
a known הלכה halachic authority and even though he was quoting ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish who quoted רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, they wanted to
know if they could rely on this teaching. מחוי להו רב ינאי
בריה דרבי ישמעאל, machvei lehu Rav Yannai brei de-Rabbi Yishmael, so רב
ינאי Rav Yannai signaled to them like did a hand signal to
say, עלי ועל צוארי, alai ve-al tzavari, like he probably did like
this, like let it be on my shoulders if this goes wrong.
Like I guess means if anybody dies as a result, because that
was the concern of גילוי. giluy. But anyway, but he was saying
yes, you can rely on this teaching. Okay, so so הלכה halachically
yes, it could be both, but I think it might also suggest
I mean the fact that this is a guy that is dying
and these are health concerns, I wonder if there's a subtext of
that. But whether it's הלכה halachic or for the סכנה sakana issue,
he said yes, you can rely on this teaching. Okay, יין מבושל
yayin mevushal is not a problem for גילוי. giluy. Okay. שמואל ואבלט,
Shmuel and Avlat, now שמואל Shmuel and אבלט, Avlat, who was a
non-Jew, הוה יתבי, hava yasvi, and they were sitting. אייתו לקמייהו חמרא
מבשלא, aisu lekameihu chamra mevashla, they brought יין מבושל yayin mevushal in
front of them. סלק ידיה, salak yadei, this אבלט Avlat was very
knew the Jewish הלכה halacha and was very concerned not to טריף
treif up שמואל Shmuel's wine, so he pulled his hand away. He
didn't want to touch the wine. סלק ידיה, salak yadei, אמר ליה
שמואל, amar lei Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel said to him, הרי אמרו
יין מבושל אין בו משום יין נסך. harei amru yayin mevushal ein
bo mishum yayin nesech. I don't understand, why didn't you learn the
הלכה? halacha? So יין מבושל yayin mevushal is not a problem, so
it's okay, you can touch it. אמתיה דרבי חייא, amteih de-Rabbi Chiya,
so now so back to the issues of גילוי, giluy, the maidservant
of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, איגלויי לה ההוא חמרא מבשלא, igluyei lah
hahu chamra mevashla,
some יין מבושל yayin mevushal was exposed to her for her, like
she was watching this wine and it was יין מבושל yayin mevushal
and then it was exposed. אתיא לקמיה דרבי חייא, atya lekameih de-Rabbi
Chiya, she came to רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. אמר לה, amar lah,
he said to her, הרי אמרו יין מבושל אין בו משום גילוי.
harei amru yayin mevushal ein bo mishum giluy. It's not a problem.
Now it's very interesting because remember in the story about the guy
on the sickbed, it was quoted by ריש לקיש Resh Lakish in
the name of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and here we have a
direct story in the name of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Not only
do you have a direct story in the name of רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is saying they said, meaning רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya is attributing it to an earlier teaching, even earlier
than himself. Okay. שמעיה דרב אדא בר אהבה, shama de-Rav Ada bar
Ahava, the servant of רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Ada bar Ahava,
איגלא ליה חמרא מזיגא, igla lei chamra meziga, so he had יין
מזוג yayin mazug mixed exposed, which is what we said before, that's
where we started, that that wasn't a problem. The snakes only like
the hard stuff.
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa said,
לא אמרן אלא דמזיג טובי. lo amran ela de-mazig tuva. I'm sorry,
אמר ליה, amar lei, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, thank you. Where were
we? מזיגא. meziga. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Ada bar Ahava said to him, הרי אמרו יין מזוג אין
בו משום גילוי, harei amru yayin mazug ein bo mishum giluy, not
a problem, it's not a problem of גילוי giluy if it's been
mixed. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa
said, לא אמרן, lo amran, wait a minute, we only said that,
אלא דמזיג טובי, ela de-mazig tuva, if it's like very well mixed.
It doesn't say how well is well mixed. But meaning like there's
a lot of water. But wouldn't you say the opposite? I don't
know, Michael. אבל מזיג ולא מזיג, aval mazig ve-lo mazig, if it's
only a small amount of water, שתי, shatei, the snakes will like
it and drink. So גמרא Gemara says, ומזיג ולא מזיג משתי, u-mazig
ve-lo mazig mishati, one minute, even if it's only slightly watered down,
since when will the snakes drink from it? והא רבה בר רב
הונא הוה קא אזיל בארבא, ve-ha Rabba bar Rav Huna hava ka
azil be-arba, רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna was going
in a boat, והוה נקיט חמרא בהדיה, ve-havi nakit chamra bahadeih, and
he... he had a whole like whatever cask of wine with him,
he was having wine, he had wine with him, וחזייה לההוא חיויא
דצייב ואתי v'chazyei l'hahu chivya d'tzayiv v'ati and then he saw a
snake cutting through the water to come and attack the boat to
drink the wine, I kid you not. ואתי אמר ליה לשמעיה v'ati
amar lei l'shamayei he said to his attendant, "סמי עיני דידן sami
eynei didan poke out the eye of that snake," which is like
a metaphor meaning do something to frustrate its intentions. So שקיל דדן
shakil didan of that, שקיל קלי shakil kali he took a little,
he took a little water, ושרדיה v'shardyei and he put it into
the wine, וסליקי לחוריה v'salikei l'churei and then the snake saw this
and turned around and said, "Ehh, it's watered down," and he went
the other way. So anyway, so you see that snakes don't like
wine even if it's discerning snakes.
Yes, he said they're discerning. You see, he said, "Are they snakes
or are they like we look at different people and we're like,
'He's a snake'?" Ah, no, I don't think swimming through the water,
I think it's talking about some sea creature here. Anyway, it's swimming
through the water. So anyway, so you see that even a little
water down they don't like it. So הגמרא ha-Gemara says, "No, it
doesn't mean they won't drink it if it's watered down, but אחיא
מסר נפשיה a-chaya masar nafshyei if it's really raw, if it's strong,
then they're willing to like risk their life to, you know, cut
through the water and jump on a boat. אמיזיגא a-miziga if it's
mixed, לא מסר נפשיה lo masar nafshyei they're not going to like,
you know, take any risks, these snakes, but they'll still drink from
it if nobody's attending to it." Okay, so now we're still saying
that that a little bit mixed is a problem, a lot mixed
is not. Now הגמרא ha-Gemara says one minute, even though מילתא דמגולה
milta d'megula water, right, ומזיגא לא
מסר נפשיה u-miziga lo masar nafshyei right, okay, that's the point you
were making, Michael. So Michael was making a point that snakes will
also drink straight water and they'll drink straight wine, but mixed they
don't like it. That's right. All right. Okay, anyway, so הגמרא ha-Gemara
says ומזיגא לא מסר נפשיה u-miziga lo masar nafshyei one minute, since
when do they not are they not willing to take risks just
for the sake of mixed wine? והא רב ינאי הוה בההוא חבורא
v'ha Rav Yannai hava b'hahu chabura ואמרי לה בר הדיי הוה בההוא
חבורא v'amrei lah bar Haddaya hava b'hahu chabura
so either Rav Yannai or Bar Haddaya was in this place, ביה
חבורא. bei chabura. חבורא chabura is a mount, I do know. והוו
יתבי והוו קא שתו חמרא v'havu yasvi v'havu ka shatu chamra and
they were sitting and drinking wine, מזיגא miziga mixed wine. פש ליה
חמרא בכובא pash lei chamra b'chuva and a little wine was left
in the barrel, וצררוהו בפורקא v'tzaruru b'faruka and they bound up the
barrel, they put a cover on the barrel like with some type
of a cloth, וחזייה לההוא חיויא v'chazyei l'hahu chivya and then they
saw a certain snake דשקיל מיא ורמא בכובא d'shakil maya u-rama b'chuva
so these snakes, I don't know, it sounds like the snake before
the sin of the Garden of Eden that he had appendages and
he was able to do things, I don't know. They somehow, some
snake, maybe I don't know what they mean by this. Anyways, coming
and throwing water into the barrel to get the wine level to
rise, so somehow maybe through the cloth the water was going in
and the wine level was going to rise and he was going
to get access to the wine. עד דמלא בכובא ad d'mala b'chuva
until it filled up the barrel, וסליק חמרא עילויה דפורקא v'salik chamra
ilvyei d'faruka and the wine floated to the
top, so it floated even above the seal, the cover, whatever thing
they had covering it like some cloth and maybe it rose above
it, ושתי v'shati and he drank it, the snake. So you see
that snakes actually care about watered down wine, even a lot watered
down. So הגמרא ha-Gemara says אמרי amri no, here's how you can
explain it: דמזיג איהו שתי d'mazig ihu shati if he mixes the
wine, if you know, "I need to mix my own wine," then
he'll drink it. דמזיג אחרינא לא שתי d'mazig achrina lo shati but
if we mix the wine he won't drink it. So הגמרא ha-Gemara
says אמר רב אשי ואיתימא רב משארשיא amar Rav Ashi v'iteima Rav
Mesharshya I love this answer: פירוקא לסכנתא peruka l'sakanta you're going to
get some teretz for something that's a health issue? Like if it
was a halakhic issue and you want to give some d'chak teretz,
"This is talking about this case and here's some hair-splitting difference," maybe.
But like if it's a health issue, don't give me these crazy
answers. Like that's what, really? Don't give some teretz for a health
issue. So אמר amar so therefore הגמרא ha-Gemara pushes, it seems to
say there's evidence that snakes actually like mixed wine. So הגמרא'ס ha-Gemara's
conclusion is fine. אמר רבא הלכתא יין מזוג יש בו משום גילוי
ויש בו משום יין נסך amar Rava hilchata yayin mazug yesh bo
mishum giluy v'yesh bo mishum yayin nesech fine, we'll take back what
we said before. Mixed wine is a problem for exposing and you
know what, we never said otherwise, but let's make it clear now,
it's also a problem for yayin nesech. A little bit mixed, sure
they'll still use that for libations. So
mixed wine is a problem for both. אבל יין מבושל אין בו
משום גילוי ואין בו משום יין נסך aval yayin mevushal ein bo
mishum giluy v'ein bo mishum yayin nesech that goes to what we
said, that certainly not a problem for yayin nesech and it's also
not a problem for exposure. Okay, another story. שמעיה דרב חלקיא בר
טובי shamayei d'Rav Chelkiya bar Tuvi the attendant of Rav Chelkiya bar
Tuvi, איגלאי ליה כסתא דמיא iglai lei kasta d'maya so he had
a certain like whatever flask of water that was exposed. So here's
an example about water being exposed. והוה ניים גביה v'hava nayem gabyei
and he was snoozing off, he was like under a tree, taking
a little siesta, and there was some exposed water in a flask,
you know, that he had, or whatever, and אתא לקמיה דרב חלקיא
בר טובי ata l'kamei d'Rav Chelkiya bar Tuvi so the question is,
he wasn't watching it, it wasn't covered, but he was sleeping nearby
it. Is that considered exposed water? אתא לקמיה דרב חלקיא בר טובי
ata l'kamei d'Rav Chelkiya bar Tuvi he came to Rav Chelkiya bar
Tuvi, אמר ליה הרי אמרו אימת ישן עליהם amar lei harei amru
eimat yashen aleihem so he said it's not a problem, even if
somebody is sleeping, that keeps the snakes away, the fear of a
sleeping... person is on them. והני מילי ביממא ve-hani milei b'yemama but
that's only in the daytime because they're afraid to get next to
a person even if he's asleep. אבל בליליא aval b'leilya in the
night לא lo it's not a problem. הגמרא ha-Gemara says ולא היא
ve-lo hi that's not true. לא שנא ביממא ולא שנא בליליא lo
shna b'ymama ve-lo shna b'leilya אימת ישן עליהם. eimas yashen aleihem. It's
not true. Even in nighttime... oh excuse me, לא אמרינן. lo amrinan.
Thank you. The last two words matter. It doesn't matter daytime or
nighttime. Thank you, Michael. Even in the daytime, thank you Michael, being
asleep doesn't help. You have to be awake like some חומרא. chumra.
רב לא שתי מבי ארמאה. Rav lo shati mi-bei arma'a. Now רב
Rav would not drink from the wine from or water, excuse me,
from the house of a non-Jew. אמר לא זהירי בגילוי. amar lo
zeiri b'gilui. They're not careful about keeping their not keeping their water
exposed. So it's a danger issue. So he wouldn't even drink water
in the house of a non-Jew. מבי ארמלתא mi-bei armalta it's a
little play ארמאה arma'a which is a non-Jew and ארמלתא armalta it's
a widow. From the house of a widow שתי shati he would
drink because here's a general suspicion, do women know have know the
הלכה? halacha? Some an assumption that only guys, this person has never
been in anybody's kosher kitchen where it's completely the women that are
keeping the, protecting all the כשרות kashrus and as you know the
רב Rav Soloveitchik's wife once said, like you and your שלחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch are going to treif up my kitchen. Like women are
totally the gatekeepers of the כשרות. kashrus. But anyway here the assumption
is is that the men know the הלכה, halacha, the women don't.
So maybe so if this is a widowed woman and she's in
her own household, like if she was you know unmarried she'd be
in her father's house or whatever. But here's a woman that is
running her own household but she's widowed. Can we assume that she's
keeping these laws and not exposing the water? So that he would
drink. מבי ארמלתא mi-bei armalta where were we, מבי ארמלתא שתי mi-bei
armalta shati he would. אמר שיבשתא דגברא נקיטא. amar shibshta d'gavra nakita.
Yeah, they're following in the habits of their husband while their husband
was alive, he made sure that they would keep the water not
exposed and even after he's dead they'll keep to that. שמואל לא
שתי מיא מבי ארמלתא. Shmuel lo shati maya mi-bei armalta. שמואל Shmuel
would not drink water from the house of widow. אמר ליכא אימתא
דגברא. amar leika eimta d'gavra. So this is there's an echo here,
right? The snake having the fear of of the person and the
snake, the man, the woman, it's all very Garden of Eden, okay,
in some say that the first that the עץ הדעת Etz ha-Da'at
was a was wine anyway, was a grape because that always because
that always leads to sin. So I don't know what's going on
here, it feels very Garden of Eden. Anyway, so he says yes
once her husband is dead she's not going to be careful. She's
going to keep the water exposed. She's not afraid of her husband
anymore. ולא מכסיא ve-lo machasya she won't cover it. מיא. maya. אבל
מבי ארמאה aval mi-bei arma'a water from the house of a non-Jew
שתי shati he would drink it. נהי דגילויא לא קפידי nehi d'giluya
lo kapidi they're not afraid of exposure for snakes, but אמנקרותא מיא
קפידי a-mankruta maya kapidi they are afraid about cleanliness. They don't want
dust and dirt to get into it, so they'll keep it covered
anyway. So apparently Jewish widows aren't concerned even for cleanliness. I don't
know how many houses he's been to. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some
say רב לא שתי מיא מבי ארמאה אבל מבי ארמלתא שתי Rav
lo shati maya mi-bei arma'a aval mi-bei armalta shati that רב Rav
would not drink from the non-Jews but would drink from the widows.
ושמואל לא שתי מיא לא מבי ארמאה ולא מבי ארמלתא. ve-Shmuel lo
shati maya lo mi-bei arma'a ve-lo mi-bei armalta. And שמואל Shmuel wouldn't
drink anybody's water. Like you can't even go and say I'll just
have the water, you know. You know, it's like the story about
the guy whatever I don't know who you want to tell it
about but anyway they say the סאטמאר Satmar guy who dies goes
up to God, you know, and he whatever and like there there's
a סעודה seuda of the לויתן Levyatan and the שור הבר Shor
ha-Bor and he says I'll just have the water. Anyway, אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי. amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. All right, so רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said anyway but שמואל Shmuel
couldn't even just have the water. Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi שלוש יינות
הן ואין בהן משום גילוי. shalosh yeinos hen ve-ein bahem mishum gilui.
There are three
wines and they're not problem of of exposure, not because of being
watered down or being cooked but because of just the like the
grain like like the type of wine it is. ואלו הן ve-eilu
hen these are they: חד chad sharp, מר mar bitter, מתוק matok
and sweet. חד chad is תילא חריפא tila charifa like very is
תילא. tila.
תילא חריפא tila charifa yes, sharp תילא tila I what did they
say תילא tila is there? Some type of an additive or something.
רש״י Rashi just says it means sharp wine. But acrid wine, yeah.
Acrid? Yes and yeah there's an Arabic word, the same word in
Arabic literally means sharp wine. Okay fine, acrid wine דמפצי זיקא de-mafzi
zika and it is so sharp and acrid that it'll cause the
actual flasks to burst. Okay מר mar bitter that's sharp. Bitter is
ירקתא. yarketa. ירקא yarka which apparently means from unripe grapes. Okay at
least that's the the what I saw looking up in a Soncino.
מתוק matok sweet is חוליא. chulya. Okay so is sweet from sweet
grapes. These are vegetables as ירקא. yarka. Oh really? Okay anyway so
right but anyway Soncino says it means unripe grapes and חוליא chulya
רש״י Rashi says are grapes that have been exposed too much to
the sun and therefore they're overly sweet. So it's basically Manischewitz. Okay
so highly sweet wine is not a problem of גילוי. gilui. Snakes
are very discerning. Presumably it would still be a problem of יין
נסך yayin nesech of סתם יינם stam yeinam but it would not
be a problem of גילוי. gilui. רב חמא מחוי לעילויי. Rav Chama
machvi l'iluwei. Now רב חמא Rav Chama when he described these three
categories described describe them in ways that they were like good wines
that fit these categories. חד, Chad, what's sharp? חמר ופלפלין, Chamar Upilpulin,
wine with pepper in it. But again, snakes won't be like that.
We like it. מר, Mar, bitter, אפסינתי, Afasinti, which some say means,
I don't know, wormwood. I don't know why that's good wine with
wormwood, wormwood sounds disgusting. I don't know what wormwood is, but it
sounds disgusting. Matt, this drink is still prepared nowadays known as absinthe.
Okay, absinthe. All right, yeah, never heard of it. All right. All
right. מתוק, Matok, sweet, is מי ברג, Mei Barg, whatever is, רש״י
Rashi says it means, I forgot what does רש״י Rashi say it
means? Sweet wine. Okay, yeah, whatever, per some type of a high-quality
wine. Okay, אמר רבי שמעון... Amar Rabbi Shimon... oh, I remember now
what סנסינו Sansino said it was, was what do you call it,
like sparkling wine. So okay, like Carmine? Yeah, like the רש״י Rashi
stuff, what do they call it? The רש״י Rashi stuff that tastes
like grape juice. Okay, fine. Yes, Moscato. Okay. אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish, so said רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish, snakes know their stuff, they don't like this.
Okay. קרינה אין בו
משום גילוי. Karina Ein Bo Mishum Giluy.
קרינה, Karina, which רש״י Rashi says means sweet wine, אין בו משום
גילוי. Ein Bo Mishum Giluy. מאי קרינה? Mai Karina? What is קרינה?
Karina? אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, חמרא חלייא דאתי מאסיא, Chamra
Chalya D'ati Me'asya, sweet wine that comes from Asia. אמר
רבא ובמקומו, Amar Rava Uvimkomo, but Assia, oh, I said it's not
they don't say it's Asia, they say Assia. רש״י Rashi says Asia.
I think it's I think that's how it's normally understood to refer
to Asia, maybe Asia Minor. Asia Minor, yeah. אמר רבא ובמקומו יש
בו משום גילוי. Amar Rava Uvimkomo Yesh Bo Mishum Giluy. In its
where it's actually grown, these grapes and made this wine, there it
is a problem. מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama? חמר מדינה הוא, Chamar Medina
Hu, because the snakes there know the local wine and they're used
to it. So therefore it's it is a problem. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, האי חמרא דאקרים, Hai Chamra D'akrim, wine that has sort of
begun to turn sour, literally it means like a film has developed
on it, it's become too like vinegary. עד תלתא יומי יש בו
משום גילוי, Ad Tlasa Yomi Yesh Bo Mishum Giluy,
for the first three days it's still good enough that there is
a גילוי Giluy problem, the snakes will drink from it, ומשום יין
נסך, Umishum Yayin Nesech, and a problem about wine of non-Jews. מכאן
ואילך אין בו משום גילוי ואין בו משום יין נסך. Mikan Va'eilach
Ein Bo Mishum Giluy Ve'ein Bo Mishum Yayin Nesech.
It's already like vinegar and it's not a problem. Again, assuming that
the non-Jew did not own it from beforehand. ונהרדעי אמרי, Vinahardei Amri,
and the Nehardeans say, אפילו לבתר תלתא יומי חיישינן משום גילוי. Afilu
Livatar Tlasa Yomi Chashinan Mishum Giluy. It might be true about יין
נסך, Yayin Nesech, after three days we say it's not a problem,
but it's still a problem of גילוי. Giluy. מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama?
זימנין דמיקרי ושתי, Zimnin Dimikrei Ushati, sometimes snakes do drink from it
and we have to be extra careful about things related to danger.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the rabbis taught, יין תוסס, Yayin Toses, here
you go, Michael, wine that is like it's sort of like bubbling
wine, but what it really means is unfermented wine, grape juice, אין
בו משום גילוי. Ein Bo Mishum Giluy.
It's not a problem of גילוי. Giluy. So we're going to start
with גילוי Giluy before we get to סתם יינם. Stam Yeinam. Now
I do have to say, by the way, that there is a
difference between unfermented wine and grape juice. Our, I mean yes, unfermented
wine is grape juice, but the difference is grape juice after because
it's pasteurized, forget the הלכות Halachos of מבושל, Mevushal, doesn't have the
ability to ferment. So and and therefore there's a big question and
the גמרא Gemara for example says that you can make קידוש Kiddush
on unfermented wine even if it's the day after it's been pressed,
which you think means oh that's totally grape juice, it is not
פשוט Pashut that you can make קידוש Kiddush on grape juice. Grape
juice is not unfermented wine. Grape juice will never ferment. Okay, but
anyway but so that's important to know that that's a very possible
distinction, but למעשה L'maaseh we treat it as the same. We make
some, you know, we make הבדלה Havdalah and קידוש Kiddush on on
grape juice even though it's been pasteurized. And also you know in
terms of non-Jews touching it, so if they own it, if they
own it before it's been pasteurized, that is the case that is
a
problem, and if they own it because
it's still wine, it's unfermented wine but it's still wine. And if
they touch it after it's been pasteurized it's already מבושל. Mevushal. So
you know, okay, but what about the grape juice additives that you
see in like you know whatever it is some of these Tropicana
things? So what is it? If it has a הכשר, Hechsher, then
that means that they're doing it in a way that it was
מראש מבושל Meirosh Mevushal before they got it and they used it,
yeah. Not only that but the Welch who created Welch's grape juice
was also a Christian minister who created pasteurized
grape juice specifically so that his churches and other churches would not
be using alcohol in their services during the Prohibition or because no,
this is in the 19th century. Well he just didn't like the
idea of alcohol. They didn't want to have alcohol because it was
like sinful. Because it was sinful. Interesting. And so the reason he
did pasteurization was not for safety but to make the חילוק Chiluk
between unpasteurized wine and grape juice exactly for that reason. Yeah, interesting.
Okay, I mean unfermented wine is אסור, Assur, grape juice is מותר.
Mutar. It's interesting. Okay, fine. So now, right, right, Michael wants to
say something. The promise is the wine would ferment. Not if you
pasteurize it well enough. But okay, but wait, okay, anyway Michael, moving
on. Right, I understand. That's what I said. He didn't want to
use unfermented wine, he wanted to use דוקא davka grape juice. Yes.
Okay, yes. There's a concept of תירוש. tirosh. It's also like some
grape juice. Where does that fall in? Like יין תוסס? yayin toses?
Yeah. I don't... I didn't think תירוש tirosh was unfermented.
I thought it was just wine.
I thought it was... Okay, maybe there's some different category, I did
not think it was unfermented. Okay, so where we are now, just
to understand what you just said, so that you know, we are,
we do have to, if it's...
this grape... whatever... grape drink... yes, unfermented wine, אין בו משום גילוי.
ein bo mishum gillui. It's a problem of... it's a problem of
יין נסך. yayin nesech. It is a problem of יין נסך, yayin
nesech, okay? It's not a problem of גילוי. gillui. וכמה תסיסתו, ve-chama
tsisato, how long is it considered to still be in its unfermented,
purely unfermented form, and therefore not a problem of גילוי? gillui? ג'
ימים, gimel yamim, three days. השחליים אין בהם משום גילוי. ha-shachalayim ein
ba-hem mishum gillui. שחליים, shachalayim, which is, what do they say that
it is? Cress or something? Cress is not a problem of גילוי
gillui because snakes don't like it. ובני גולה נהגו בהן איסור, u-venei
golah nahagu ba-hen issur, but in... those in the exile treated it
as forbidden. ולא אמרן אלא דלית בהו חלא. ve-lo amran ela de-leit
behu chala. Now, that's only... when did they treat it as forbidden
and they were referred that the snakes would eat from it when
there's no vinegar? אבל אית בהו חלא, aval it behu chala,
if vinegar was added to it, מגרי בהו, magrei behu, then that
the... like is counter... the... that attacks the snake or whatever, you
know, snakes don't like that and they don't drink it. כותח הבבלי,
kutach ha-bavli,
Babylonian dip, which is like some type of a, you know, bread
crumbs and... and yogurt and other types of stuff. Okay. אין בהם
משום גילוי, ein ba-hem mishum gillui, is not a problem of exposing.
ובני גולה נהגו בהן איסור, u-venei golah nahagu ba-hen issur, but in
exile, meaning outside of Israel, they treated it as forbidden. ואמר רב
מנשיא, ve-amar Rav Menashya, אי אית בה ניקורי, ei it bah nikkurei,
if there by the way is signs that a snake has actually...
like there's puncture marks in it, like teeth marks in it, חיישינן,
chashinan, then, oh, then we have to be afraid that a snake
drank from it. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר שמואל, Amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Ashi amar Shmuel, מי טיפ טיפ אין בו משום גילוי.
mei tip tip ein bo mishum gillui. Tip, tip, tip. So water
that is... if you have a barrel and there's water that's constantly
dripping into the barrel, or wine that's constantly dripping, that sound will
keep the snake away and it's not a problem. אמר רב אשי
והוא דעביד טיפ להדי טיפ טיפ. Amar Rav Ashi ve-hu de-avid tip
lahadei tip tip. It's like it has to be constant. Tip, tip,
tip, tip, tip, tip, tip, tip. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי
אמר שמואל, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Shmuel, פי תאנים אין
בהם משום גילוי. pi te'einim ein ba-hem mishum gillui. If you have
a fig, and you know, and you know, you... it's like because
you removed the... whatever, the... what's it called, the twig, the stem,
it's a little exposed, you don't have to be worried that the
snake is going to bite into it like where it's... where the
skin has been broken. Okay. כמאן? Ke-man? Who's this going like? כי
האי תנא. Ki hai tanna. דתניא, De-tanya, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, אוכל אדם ענבים ותאנים בלילה ואינו חושש. ochel adam anavim u-te'einim
ba-layla ve-eino choshesh. A person can eat grapes and figs at night
and doesn't have to be afraid that, you know, a snake will
come and eat from it... and when, you know, if he's not
looking. משום שנאמר, mishum she-ne'emar, שומר פתאים ה'. shomer peta'im Hashem. God
watches over the simple. Of course, if you're sitting there eating the
figs and the grapes, you would think that your presence might scare
away the snakes, but that's not the point. אמר רב ספרא משום
רבי יהושע דרומיא, Amar Rav Safra mishum Rabbi Yehoshua Deromaya, ואמרי לה
רבי יהושע בן לוי, ve-amrei lah Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, ג' מיני
ארס הן. gimel minei eres hen. There are three types of poison,
snake poison. של בחור, shel bachur, from young snakes, שוקע, shokei'a,
is heavy and it's like dense and it's powerful and it sinks
to the bottom of the wine or the food. של בינוני, shel
beinoni, of a middle-aged snake, מפעפע, mefa'pei'a, it sort of... it's like...
it's in the middle of the... it sinks to the middle. It's
not too heavy, not too light. ושל זקן, ve-shel zaken, and of
an elderly snake, צף. tzaf. It's very... it's not so powerful and
it floats at the top of whatever it bit into. למימרא דכמה
דקשיש כחיש חילה? Le-meimra de-chama de-kashish kachish cheileh? Are you telling me
the older a snake is, the weaker it is? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, ג' כל זמן שמזקינין גבורה מתוספת בהן. shelosha kol
zeman she-mazkinin gevurah mitossefet ba-hen.
There are three that the older they get, the stronger they get.
אלו הן: Elu hen: דג, נחש וחזיר. dag, nachash, ve-chazir.
A fish, you know, keeps on growing and growing and growing. A
snake also grows, you know, you ever go to the... the zoo
and you see these old snakes, right? They're huge. And a boar,
a wild boar, you ever see these old, and they're huge, right?
So the גמרא Gemara says, כוח אוסופי הוא דקמוסיף. koach ossufei hu
de-ka-mossif. Yes.
The animal gets stronger, bigger. ארסיה erseih but its poison, כליש, kalish,
gets weaker. So now the גמרא Gemara says, של בחור שוקע למאי
הלכתא? shel bachur shokei'a le-mai hilcheta? Why do I care to know
that the poison of a young snake sinks? דתניא, De-tanya, חבית שנתגלתה.
chavit she-nitgalta.
Let's say you have a barrel that was exposed. אף על פי
ששתו ממנו תשעה ולא מתו. af al pi she-shatu mimenu tish'ah ve-lo
metu. Nine people drank from it and they didn't die. So you
could say this clearly proves that no snake has drunk from it,
cause nine people already drank from it. לא ישתה ממנו עשירי. lo
yishteh mimenu asiri. Don't drink the tenth. You know why? Because if
a young snake drank from it, the poison is all at the
bottom. So the fact that nine people drank isn't a proof cause
the poison is all at... could all be at the bottom. מעשה
היה, Ma'aseh hayah, there was a story ששתו ממנו תשעה ולא מתו.
she-shatu mimenu tish'ah ve-lo metu. Nine drank from it and didn't die.
ושתה עשירי ומת. ve-shatah asiri va-met. And the tenth drank and died.
אמר רבי ירמיה זהו שוקע. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya zehu shokei'a. This is
the poison that sinks to the bottom. וכן אבטיח. ve-chen avatiach. Similarly
by like a melon שנתגלתה. she-nitgalta. That was exposed. אף על פי
שאכלו ממנו ט' בני אדם. af al pi she-achlu mimenu tesha benei
adam. Even though nine people ate from it ולא מתו ve-lo metu
and didn't die. לא יאכל ממנו עשירי. lo yo'chal mimenu asiri. Don't
eat a tenth person because it'll be... the poison might have sunk
to the bottom. מעשה היה ואכלו ממנו תשעה ולא מתו. Ma'aseh hayah
ve-achlu mimenu tish'ah ve-lo metu. Nine drank and... and didn't die. ואכל
עשירי ומת. ve-achal asiri va-met. And the tenth one ate it and
died. ורש"י ve-Rashi says, by the way, that's also why we have
to know... So that there's a poison that stays at the middle
level, because don't say, well look, three people have drunk from it,
so if the poison isn't at the top and if the poison
isn't at the bottom, I'm safe, I'll just drink from the middle.
No, there's poison that could be at the bottom, poison that could
be at the middle, and poison that could be at the top.
Okay, אמר רבי זהו שוקע. Amar Rebbe zehu shoke'ah. Okay, so let's
just wrap up, just got one more minute. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
מים שנתגלו הרי זה לא ישפכם ברשות הרבים. Mayim shenitgalu harei zeh
lo yishpechem bereshut harabim. If it's been exposed and it might have
poison in it, don't spill it out into the public domain; somebody
will walk on it barefoot and it'll get into their body. ולא
ירביץ בהן את הבית, Velo yarbitz bahen et habayit, don't use it
to settle the dust in the house, same reason. ולא יגבל בהן
את הטיט, Velo yagbel bahen et hatit, don't even make plaster with
it. Who knows, maybe some of it will seep out; it's like
lead in the paint in the walls. ולא ישקם לא לבהמתו ולא
לבהמת חברו, Velo yashkem lo livahemto velo livahemat chavero, don't even let
your animal drink from it. Why should you be killing your animal,
and then it'll get into the meat maybe, or your friend's animal.
ולא ירחץ בהן פניו ידיו ורגליו, Velo yirchatz bahen panav yadav veraglav,
and don't wash your hands, face, and feet from it. אחרים אומרים,
Acherim omrim, others say מקום שיש סירטא אסור, makom sheyesh sirta asur,
you can't wash your body where there's some crevice. אין סירטא, ein
sirta, a place in your body that there's no crevice, מותר mutar
is permissible. I guess they weren't afraid of it going through the
pores of your skin. אחרים היינו תנא קמא, Acherim hainu Tanna Kama,
so the Gemara says isn't that the same? Isn't face, hand, and
feet places where there are crevices in your body? איכא בינייהו גב
היד וגב הרגל, Ika beinei-hu gav hayad vegav haregel, now presumably the
back of your hand doesn't have a crevice, so according to this
it would be okay, ורומני
דאפי, veromni de'apei, and also the soft part of your face, apparently
like maybe your cheek or something, so there's no crevice. So if
you go by the crevice rule that would be allowed, but if
you go by the hand, feet, and face rule it would not.
אמר מר לא ישקם לא לבהמתו ולא לבהמת חברו, Amar Mar lo
yashkem lo livahemto velo livahemat chavero, don't give it to your animal
or your friend's animal. והתניא, Vehatanya, but we have a Baraita that
says אבל משקהו לבהמת עצמו, aval mashkehu livahemat atzmo, you can give
it to your own animal. Presumably if you want to kill your
own animal it's your business. No, כי תניא ההיא לשונרא. ki tanya
hahi leshunra. No, that means you can give it to your cat,
because cats since they can eat snakes aren't affected by snake poison,
that's the assumption. אי הכי דחבריה נמי, ei hachi dechavrei nami, so
give it to your friend's cat. No, דחבריה כחיש, dechavrei kachish, so
your friend's cat, it might not die but it'll get weaker. דידיה
נמי כחיש, didei nami kachish, so your own cat'll get weaker. No,
הדר ברי. hadar bari. No, it'll get better. דחבריה נמי הדר ברי,
dechavrei nami hadar bari, so give it to your friend's cat, it'll
also get better. No, זימנין דבעי לזבוני ומפסד ליה מיניה. zimnin deba'ei
lizvonei umaphsed lei minei. No, your cat, you can decide 'I'll let
it get sick, it'll get better,' that's your own חשבון. cheshbon. But
your friend's cat, if it gets sick, it gets weaker, maybe he
wants to sell it and now because it's weaker he can't get
as good of a price. Okay, we will end there.